It has been written ...
since the beginning of time ...
even onto these ancient stones ...
that evil , supernatural creatures exist ...
in a world of darkness .
And it is also said ...
man , using the magic power ...
of the ancient runic symbols ...
can call forth these powers of darkness ...
the demons of hell .
Through the ages , men have feared and worshipped these creatures .
The practice of witchcraft , the cults of evil ...
have endured and exist to this day .
Fifteen . Two and three makes five .
- I must see Dr. Karswell at once . - Who shall I say is calling ?
Professor Harrington . Tell him it 's most urgent .
I 'm afraid Mr. Karswell is not at home , sir .
I know he 's here . Tell him I won 't leave until he does see me .
- I 'm very sorry , sir . - Well , go back and say ...
- Karswell . - That 's all right , Bates .
Please , come in . This way .
- Good evening . - Good evening .
Mother ...
Well , I 'll go and see about some tea .
That won 't be necessary . We shall only be a minute .
Call it off , Karswell . Stop this thing you 've started ...
and I 'll admit publicly I was totally wrong and that you were totally right .
It 's very gratifying to hear that , but some things ...
are more easily started than stopped .
But I 've heard it . I 've seen it . I know it 's real !
You involved me in a public scandal .
I protested .
You said , " Do your worst , " and that 's precisely what I did .
Please , Karswell . I 'll stop this investigation .
When Holden arrives , I 'll tell him I 've made a mistake .
I 'll send a statement to the newspapers .
No more newspapers . All I ask for is privacy for myself and my followers .
- Well , I promise . - All right . That 's good enough .
Then you 'll stop this ?
You 've still got that parchment I gave you ?
The runic symbols ? No , they burned . I couldn 't stop it .
I see . Well , I think perhaps you 'd better go home .
- Then you will help me ? - I 'll do all that I can .
- Karswell , if you only knew . - I do know .
Thank you .
- Good night , Mrs. Karswell . - Good night .
Thank you again .
Good-bye , Professor .
- Yes , sir ? - Do you have one of those eye masks ?
I must get some sleep . That light keeps shining in my eyes .
I 'm afraid we don 't . Would you like a pill ?
No , thanks . I 'm trying to cut down .
Excuse me .
I can 't get out .
- Sorry . - Good .
Could I change my seat ? I can 't sleep ...
and I seem to be bothering the gentleman in front of me .
I 'm afraid it 's impossible . We 're full up .
Oh . Thank you .
Thanks .
Anytime .
Here they come .
Dr. Holden ? I 'm Lloyd Williamson .
- Professor Harrington 's personal aide . - How are you ?
I 'm so glad I 'd be able to meet you here , sir .
The professor had planned to meet you here himself , but he ...
- Well ... - Dr. Holden ?
We 're the press , sir . Could you spare a few minutes ?
- What makes me news ? - Ghosts .
What exactly is the function of this convention you 're attending ?
Investigation of international reports on paranormal psychology .
" Para " what psychology ?
Just say mind-reading , fortune-telling , spirits and zombies .
What are your views on those people in the States who claim to be reincarnated ?
Bunk . Under hypnosis ...
people are unusually susceptible to the power of suggestion .
Do all your delegates share your views on the supernatural ?
There are probably some who don 't .
Ask Williamson here . He 'll probably know .
Do you believe those who don 't to be fakers ?
Let 's say some people honestly believe in the supernatural .
But according to you , they 're wrong .
- That 's right . - What about the other delegates ?
We haven 't got time . I have a car waiting outside .
- One thing more , Doctor . - Yes ?
Take it kind of easy on our ghosts . We English are sort of fond of them .
Sure . Some of my best friends are ghosts .
Operator , I 'm still waiting for my number .
I 'm sorry . The number you requested is reported out of order .
Could you check it , then ? It 's to Professor Harrington 's house .
That is the correct number , but I 'm sorry . The line is out of order .
Oh . Thank you .
Sorry to keep you waiting , Williamson .
You were saying Professor Harrington couldn 't come .
I 'm afraid I have some terrible news for you .
Professor Harrington was found dead this morning .
Found dead ?
Sorry to disturb you , but there 's so much to do and so little time .
I 'll be right out .
The police say that Professor Harrington was electrocuted .
Somehow , his car ran into a power line outside his house .
It was a terrible accident .
He must 've died instantly .
- The services will be held tomorrow . - I 'll be there .
This is Mark O 'Brien . He 's been working with Professor Harrington .
- He 'll continue to do so with you . - Fine .
You 'll have to forgive me . I had a little sleep to catch up on .
- Of course . - Sit down . I won 't be very long .
- What is this ? - Part of O 'Brien 's research ...
which is tied up with the Karswell Devil Cult investigation .
I see . Let me get some clothes on .
I wrote Professor Harrington recently that if he wanted to find the key ...
to Karswell 's phony supernatural power , all he had to do ...
was check the psychological makeup of some of his followers .
I know , but we ran into difficulty .
The one cult member we persuaded to speak up ...
a farmer named Rand Hobart ...
was arrested several weeks ago as an alleged murderer .
He can still be useful .
I 'm afraid not . His mind is in total collapse .
He 's in a state of catatonic shock and in a home for the criminally insane .
Why do you say " alleged murderer " ?
That 's just my personal view .
A short while ago at the asylum , I succeeded in rousing Hobart .
Under hypnosis , he produced this drawing .
It 's crude , but remarkably similar to these copies ...
of old woodcuts and medieval drawings ...
of a fire demon invoked by witchcraft to destroy an enemy .
You mean you think that thing committed the murder ?
I thought the purpose of our convention was to disprove that type of thinking .
- Yes , but Mark says ... - I 'll speak for myself , Llyod .
I 'm a scientist also , Dr. Holden .
I know the value of the cold light of reason .
But I also know the deep shadows that light can cast .
The shadows that can blind men to truth .
What truth ? Myths .
Demonology and witchcraft have been discredited ...
since the Middle Ages .
I wrote a book about it . That 's why I 'm here .
Then explain how an uneducated farmer like Hobart ...
could know anything about this creature ...
whose legend has persisted through civilization after civilization .
Babylonian , Baal , Egyptian ...
Sethtyphon , Persian , Asmodeus ...
Hebraich , Moloch ...
Come in .
Good evening . KT Kumar , Bombay , apologizes for being late .
That 's quite all right , Kumar . We 're just about to begin .
- This is Dr. Holden . - How do you do ?
Dr. Holden . I 'm very pleased to meet you .
Your work on hypnotism is a great favorite of mine .
Thank you . Now , we were just talking about devils and demons .
What are your views on the subject ?
I believe in them . Absolutely .
Well , now that we 're all here , let 's get down to business .
Excuse me .
- Hello ? - Holden ?
This is Julian Karswell speaking .
Speak of the devil .
- Yes , Karswell ? - I presume you know who I am .
Yes . What can I do for you ?
Simply this . The newspapers say you 're heading ...
this so-called expose of my activities ... is that true ?
Yes , that 's right .
I suggest you have some second thoughts on this .
Such as ?
Such as minding your business ... not mine or Rand Hobart 's .
Harrington agreed to this . Out of respect for him , you might do the same .
- Can you prove that ? - Had his personal assurance .
I 'm afraid you can 't have mine .
That 's unfortunate , maybe for both of us .
O 'Brien , see if you can have Hobart ...
released to us for a clinical examination under test conditions .
That 's exactly what I had in mind .
And forget this demon / monster theory of yours . It doesn 't make sense .
Karswell 's worried about what Hobart might tell us .
That makes sense .
You 'll find the library straight through , sir .
I 'm sorry , sir , but the last volume you asked for ...
The True Discoveries of the Witches and Demons ...
is not available .
What does " not available " mean ?
It should be in our restricted section .
The only known existing copy ...
is over 400 years old , you know .
Yes , I know .
It seems to be missing . Most peculiar .
I 'm having it checked .
It was mentioned in these research notes .
Never mind . I can probably find what I want in these .
I hope so , sir . I 'll do my best to trace it .
Excuse me , sir .
I couldn 't help overhearing your conversation with the librarian .
You 're interested in seeing The True Discoveries of Witches and Demons .
- Is that it ? - Yes .
I have a copy I 'll gladly put at your disposal .
Then the British Museum didn 't have the only copy .
Apparently not , Dr. Holden .
I have what is perhaps the finest library in the world ...
on witchcraft and the black arts .
- You know my name . - Oh , yes .
And you know mine . I 'm Julian Karswell .
How did you know I was here ?
Isn 't it the scientist who always calls what he can 't explain otherwise ...
by the word " coincidence " ?
Let 's call this coincidence .
I wouldn 't like to think I 'd been followed from my hotel this morning .
I assure you , you weren 't followed .
I just thought it might be profitable for both of us to meet , you see .
It 's rather difficult to talk here .
Why not come out to my place in the country ? The book 's there .
If I don 't find what I want , I might take you up on that .
Delighted .
Just one thing . Let 's understand each other .
My investigation of you and your cult ...
won 't be stopped .
But if I could make my point , I could persuade you .
I 'm not open to persuasion .
But a scientist should have an open mind .
That 's what investigations are for .
Well ...
in any event , here 's my card .
Lufford Hall . It 's near Wargrave .
I 'll be seeing you soon , I 'm sure .
Excuse me . How clumsy .
I 'm so , so sorry .
Here are your papers , sir .
- Thank you . - Good-bye .
Don 't leave it too long .
Can I help you , sir ?
Did you see that man who was just here ?
I can 't say that I did .
- What do you make of this ? - It 's a visiting card .
No , I mean the handwriting on it .
- No handwriting . - Yes , there is .
Forget it .
I can 't find anything on this card .
- Nothing at all ? - No .
I could try some absorption tests , but that would take time .
- How much time ? - Tonight ?
Fine . Call me at my hotel when it 's finished .
- Aren 't you ... - Yes , on the plane .
- Did you know the professor ? - Did you ?
Yes , I worked with him . I 'm John Holden .
Then I must talk to you . It 's very important .
I 'm Joanna Harrington . Professor Harrington was my uncle .
- My deepest sympathies . - Thank you .
- When can we meet ? - Tonight ?
- Call me at my hotel . - All right .
- 412 . Down to the left , miss . - Thank you .
- Well , come in . - Thanks .
So you really are Dr. Holden ?
All scientists don 't wear thick glasses .
I apologize for bothering you on the plane .
What was all that writing about anyway ?
Letters to my pupils about my trip to America .
I 'm a kindergarten teacher .
I 'm sorry it ended so tragically for you .
- Thank you . - Sit down , won 't you ?
- Would you like a drink ? - No , thanks .
You don 't mind if I have one , do you ? I need it .
It 's cold tonight , isn 't it ?
No , it 's hot . Quite hot .
Do you think so ?
I heard you 're continuing my uncle 's project .
- And ? - I think you ought to drop it .
You 're the second person to suggest that in one day .
- What 's your reason ? - I believe you 're in danger .
I found my uncle 's diary . It 's all in here .
- You make it sound very menacing . - It is .
I think it had something to do with my uncle 's death .
Something horrible happened to him .
Something unexplainably horrible .
- I 'd like to read it to you . - Go ahead .
" Met Karswell at Albert Hall concert . "
He puts three exclamation marks after that sentence .
Karswell can be a pretty startling character .
- You 've met him ? - This morning .
Listen to this . " Karswell most pleasant .
Lost my program during concert , and Karswell gave me his .
A nice gesture , since I save them . "
That doesn 't sound particularly menacing .
Wait .
" Today I found the parchment ...
in the concert program Karswell gave me .
It had runic symbols drawn on it . "
That 's not mysterious .
Runic symbols are the oldest form of an alphabet .
They 're found carved on ancient stones , like hieroglyphics .
They 're supposed to have magic powers . They don 't .
" The parchment acted as if it were alive .
It pulled from my hand and Flew into the fire and burned .
I think I can guess what Karswell has done to me . "
- Cigarette ? - No , thanks . There 's a lot more ...
about seeing visions of a monstrous , smoky shape ...
and feeling cold , like you said you were .
" I 'm under some kind of witch 's spell . My mind is in the balance .
Must speak to Holden about this . "
Unfortunately , you came too late .
What you 're trying to tell me is ...
your uncle was killed by witchcraft .
As a doctor , I can assure you you 're wrong .
It 's a pure case of auto-suggestion .
But the way he knew he was going to die ...
and the horrible way he actually did .
There 's not a thing that happened that couldn 't have been an accident .
You see , Miss Harrington , the shock of finding your uncle dead ...
Please don 't treat me like a mental patient who has to be humored .
I also majored in psychology .
- I 'm sorry . I didn 't mean ... - You could learn a lot from children .
They believe in things in the dark until we tell them it 's not so .
Maybe we 've been fooling them . Good night , Dr. Holden .
I 'm really quite flattered you 've taken such an interest in my welfare .
Don 't be . If I hadn 't been away , my uncle might still be alive .
- It was an accident . - I don 't believe that .
I loved my uncle very much , and I want to know exactly what happened to him .
You don 't seem to share my view . Good night .
Wait just a minute .
I 've tested this card through and through .
There 's been no chemical used on it .
Are you sure ? Couldn 't it have rubbed off in my pocket ?
Maybe , but some of it certainly would have been absorbed into the card ...
and my absorption tests would have shown it .
This card is 100 % clean . I guarantee it .
I see . Well , thank you .
How would you like to show me the way to Lufford Hall ...
and the friendly Mr. Karswell tomorrow ?
- Then you think ... - Don 't jump to conclusions .
I just wanna borrow a book from him and discuss a chemistry problem .
- Are you sure this is Karswell 's place ? - That 's what it said back there .
I don 't know what his racket is , but it pays very well .
Sounds like a human sacrifice .
Well , you remember the magic word , of course .
- Yeah ! - Now !
Abracadabra !
See ? A magic puppy .
Now , who 'd like to stroke a magic puppy ?
Another one .
It 's magic .
Just a tame magician . So that was it .
That was what ?
The answer to my chemistry problem .
Why don 't ...
Right , children . Now , just be good for a few minutes .
I shall be back .
- Holden . Delighted to see you . - I hope we 're not intruding .
Not at all . Just my annual Halloween party for the village children .
I 'll come right up .
- He 's just a nice old guy . - Perhaps he 's Santa Claus in disguise .
I didn 't recognize you .
I used to earn my living like this years ago .
You see before you Dr. Bobo the Magnificent .
Excuse me . This is Miss Joanna Harrington .
- Miss , uh , not by any chance ... - Yes . He was my uncle .
I was very sorry to hear of his accident .
He was a man of great principle .
Mother ?
I 'd like you to meet my mother . You must try her homemade ice cream .
She 's very proud of it .
- May I introduce Dr. Holden . - How do you do ?
And Miss Joanna Harrington .
Miss Harrington is a niece of Henry Harrington 's .
Dr. Holden 's going to borrow a book from my library .
- I 've asked them to stay . - How nice .
I hope you don 't mind children 's parties , my dear .
Julian 's so fond of children .
He really ought to be married , but he 's so fussy .
- You aren 't married , are you ? - No .
- Oh , Mother . - Do you like ice cream , my dear ?
- Yes , I love it . - Come with me . I 'll give you a treat .
- Would you like to try some ? - Not right now , thank you .
Say , this is quite a place you have here .
Yes , yes . Let me show you around .
Snakes and Ladders . An English game . You wouldn 't know it .
You see , if you land at the foot of the ladder , you climb up to the top .
But if you land on the head of a snake , you slide all the way down again .
Funny thing .
I always preferred sliding down the snakes to climbing up the ladders .
You 're a doctor of psychology . You ought to know the answer to that .
Maybe you 're a good loser .
I 'm not , you know . Not a bit .
Just how much do you know about this book that you 're after ?
Not very much . Only that Professor Harrington referred to it in his notes .
A remarkable work . The few men that really understood it ...
learned many strange and terrifying secrets .
Only a few ? Is it that hard to understand ?
I spent my life trying to decipher it .
The ancient sorcerers who wrote it knew their information ...
was far too valuable to entrust to any known language .
I didn 't realize what I was asking for .
You don 't believe in witchcraft ?
Do you ?
Do I believe in witchcraft ? What kind of witchcraft ?
The legendary witch that rides on the imaginary broom ?
The hex that tortures the thoughts of the victim ?
The pin stuck in the image that wastes away the mind and body ?
Also imaginary .
But where does imagination end and reality begin ?
What is this twilight ...
this half-world of the mind that you profess to know so much about ?
How can we differentiate between the powers of darkness ...
and the powers of the mind ?
- This is a stick-up ! - How terrifying .
What do I see here ? Yes , some chocolate , I do believe .
And there as well . Here we are .
Gosh ! Chocolate !
Wonderful , aren 't they ? If only we grown-ups ...
could preserve their capacity for simple joys and simple beliefs .
I see you practice white magic as well as black .
Oh , yes .
I don 't think it would be too amusing for the youngsters ...
if I conjured up a demon from hell for them .
Or for myself , for that matter .
As we 're not protected by the magic circle , we 'd both be torn to shreds .
And you 'd spoil the party .
You 're so right .
But how to prove my point .
There . It 's done .
What is ?
A magician doesn 't like to expose his magic , black or white .
- Where are the others ? - They probably went ' round by the back .
I didn 't know you had cyclones in England .
We don 't .
- You probably could use a drink . - The perfect host .
This way .
I 'm sorry . I miscalculated .
The wind 's stronger than I expected . Much too much .
You 're talking in riddles .
To prove my point .
A medieval witch 's specialty ... a wind storm .
Take my professional advice and stick to rabbits and puppy dogs .
You think I 'm mad ? Unfortunately , you won 't be able ...
to explain away your death on the 28th of this month so easily ...
with my prediction of it at this moment .
You 're really serious , aren 't you ?
You will die as I said ...
at 10 : 00 on the 28th of this month .
Your time allowed is just three days from now .
" My time allowed . "
Oh , yes , your trick with the card . Very good too .
I 'm sorry you remain so skeptical .
But as the time gets closer , mental disintegration will set in .
First , weakness and unsureness .
And then horror , as the fear of what is behind you grips your heart .
Because it 's there , Dr. Holden . It 's there !
It has been from the moment we met in the museum .
You actually believe this nonsense .
I asked you to drop this ridiculous investigation .
Perhaps you will before it 's too late .
Well , it 's nice to know that I do have a way out , Mr. Karswell .
The choice is yours .
I don 't know if the diagrams are of any use to you , dear ...
but as you see , the words make no sense at all .
- What kind of language is this ? - I really don 't know .
I didn 't know that you were interested in the black arts , Miss Harrington .
She wanted to see the books you and Dr. Holden were discussing , didn 't you ?
But we can 't read a word , can we , dear ?
- What especially interests you ? - The power of the runic symbols .
Undoubtedly , the answer to your question lies in that remarkable work .
Unfortunately , it 's unreadable . It 's written entirely in cipher .
You offered to lend it to Dr. Holden . Shall I take it to him ?
He also knows it would be useless without a word key .
The storm has ended . I 'm sure you and the doctor ...
are anxious to return to London .
Yes . You mean the party 's over ?
You 'll find him in the morning room where I left him waiting .
Well , good-bye , my dear . I 'll see ...
I 'll see you again soon , I hope .
Yes . Thank you . Good-bye .
It was a lovely party , wasn 't it ? Except for that dreadful wind .
Have I done something wrong ?
Yes , Mother .
Do sit down .
I only wanted to show her your books . I know how proud you are of them .
Yes , I know . Listen , Mother .
You believe in the supernatural .
I 've shown you some of its power and some of its danger .
- Yes , Julian . - Well , believe this also .
You get nothing for nothing .
This house , the land , the way we live ...
Nothing for nothing . My followers who pay for all of this ...
do it out of fear .
And I do what I do out of fear also .
It 's part of the price .
But if it makes you unhappy , stop it .
Give it back .
How can you give back life ?
I can 't stop it . I can 't give it back .
I can 't let anyone destroy this thing . I must protect myself .
Because if it 's not someone else 's life , it 'll be mine .
You understand , Mother ? It 'll be mine .
You 're home .
That 's the first thing you 've said for half an hour .
What 's the use of talking ? It has no effect .
- But it has . - Then what are you gonna do about it ?
Practice restraint .
I 'm gonna order a sandwich and a glass of milk and go to sleep .
How a man who 's been told he 'll die in three days can consider sleeping ...
is all the proof I need of the supernatural .
I 'm not all that brave . I 'm not all that gullible either .
- When am I gonna see you again ? - Why ?
Do you think I 'm gullible ?
But nice . When ?
Well , I 'll be too busy going through my uncle 's papers ...
I have a full day tomorrow too , but I 'd be happy ...
to accept an invitation to dinner .
Come on . Say " yes . "
I know some very interesting experiments in cause and effect .
We could discuss them as ...
as fellow scientists , of course .
- About 8 : 00 ? - Thank you . And don 't worry .
I 'll be around to see the outcome of Mr. Karswell 's remarkable prediction .
- Good night . - Good night .
Nice of you to drop in , Kumar . Good evening , Holden .
Why , Mr. Holden . Are you ill ?
- I 'm all right . Hello , Mark . - I phoned you earlier .
The authorities have been difficult about cooperating on Hobart .
We need the family to sign a release . I have it here .
If it 's gonna be that much trouble , forget it .
His memory patterns are probably worthless anyway .
Besides , I 've met this Karswell .
- He 's just a harmless faker . - You are a very skeptical man .
That 's what Karswell said .
- Care for a nightcap ? - I wouldn 't mind .
Haven 't you gentlemen heard that alcohol is the devil 's brew ?
And interested as I am in the devil , I never indulge , thank you .
O 'Brien , don 't you think that ...
skepticism is the scientific attitude ?
Oh , sometimes .
All good scientists are from Missouri .
In other words , they should continually be saying , " Show me . "
- And if you are shown ? - Then I 'll look twice .
- Like water ? - No , thank you .
The whole question of this demon monster ...
that you think shocked Hobart out of his mind ...
is a perfect example of auto-suggestion and mass hysteria .
Just the same as flying saucers .
Someone imagines that they see moving lights in the sky .
And the next thing , a thousand hysterical witnesses ...
turn up all over the world swearing that Martians are attacking us .
And now , this nonsense .
It even affects serious men like yourselves .
Sometimes , even me .
But logic ... the reality of the seeable and the touchable ...
that 's what convinces me finally .
Certainly not rumor or intuition or funny feelings .
Here 's how .
I wouldn 't dream of arguing with you .
You say , " Show me . " I say , " Look for yourself . "
You know , the devil has something here . Very pleasant .
He 's most dangerous when he 's being pleasant .
Look , Mark , I don 't want to be arbitrary ...
about this Hobart business , if you 're so set on it .
- Let me think it over , will you ? - We haven 't much time .
- This is the release form . - Thank you .
I wonder ...
if either of you could recognize this tune .
It goes something like this .
And then it goes ...
Sounds like a distortion of an Irish folk tune .
About the devil , I believe . Present devils excepted , of course .
A most odd coincidence .
For in Northern India there is a similar tune ...
which is also part of an enchantment spell .
Well , that takes care of that . I guess I must have heard it somewhere .
It kept running through my mind .
Tell me , what have you got in your program for the convention tomorrow ?
Only a few sessions on extrasensory perception .
The timetable is over there on the desk .
I 'd like to watch you work . Do you mind ?
Not at all . Be glad to have you .
Holden , you are not leaving us after the 28th , are you ?
No . Why did you ask that ?
Well , it 's just that all the pages after the 28th are torn out .
I hope we don 't run out of candles before the power lines are repaired .
Don 't you think eating by candlelight is romantic ?
Yes , but not on a night like this .
Shall we have some brandy in the living room ?
I could use something to warm me up .
Don 't say it . I know you think it 's hot in here .
No . As a matter of fact , it 's rather chilly .
Do you know The Ancient Mariner ?
Vaguely . I read it in school .
I found a copy of it in my uncle 's desk .
He underlined one part .
" Like one that on a lonesome road doth walk in fear and dread ...
because he knows a frightful fiend ...
doth close behind him tread . "
I hope you don 't read poems like that to your kindergarten class .
When it 's important that a child learn something ...
I use the most direct means available .
I get it , teach .
He scribbled a note on the next page .
I never had a kindergarten teacher as pretty as you are .
- I 'm serious . - So am I.
You wouldn 't deny a dying man a last request , would you ?
You 'll listen whether you like it or not . You haven 't much time left .
" Today I found all the pages of my desk calendar ...
torn out after October the 22nd . "
I know why . He died on the 22nd .
John , what 's the matter ?
The same thing happened to my desk calendar , after the 28th .
And I know why .
You put the two together , and they add up to a very obvious trick .
You see , when a tribal witch doctor puts a hex on his victim ...
he always lets the victim know well beforehand .
Let me see your uncle 's diary .
In case it would make you feel better ...
a parchment has to be passed ...
and the person has to take it without knowing .
My mother taught me never to take anything from strangers .
- I still don 't . - Then what killed my uncle ?
An accident with a falling power line killed him .
Then he should only have been burned .
His body was mutilated horribly .
The police said it could 've been an animal .
The only thing they didn 't say was what kind of animal .
What do you expect me to do ? Nobody 's free from fear .
I have an imagination like anyone else .
It 's easy to see a demon in every dark corner .
But I refuse to let this thing take possession of my good senses .
If this world is ruled by demons and monsters , we may as well give up now .
Nobody said we were ruled by them .
You just want me to give in to Karswell 's carefully calculated threats .
That 's exactly what he wants me to do .
Because he knows he can 't stand up to a real investigation .
If he 's so all-powerful , what 's he so afraid of ?
I wish I knew .
Are you sure Karswell never passed anything or gave you anything ...
on which the runes could have been written ?
- What if he did ? - Did he ?
Well , he could have at the museum when my notes fell to the floor .
As a matter of fact , he mentioned the museum the other day .
Yes ?
Well , he picked up the papers and handed ' em back to me .
- Where are they now ? - At my hotel , I suppose .
No .
They 're in my briefcase . I have it here .
He did give you the parchment .
- It 's trying to escape ! - It 's just the wind .
But it is trying to escape into the fire !
It 's the draft from the chimney .
What made them stop ?
I don 't know .
Pardon me . Is this the Hobart farm ?
- Is this the Hobart place ? - Get off this property !
- All I 'm trying to find out ... - You heard what I said . Get off !
They told me this was the Hobart farm . If it is , I 've got to see Mrs. Hobart .
All right . Come in .
Sit , you .
What be it you want with us ?
- Is Rand Hobart your son ? - He was my son .
You know , he hasn 't been proven to be the killer , Mrs. Hobart .
Speak your business . I 'm not interested ...
in his guilt or want of guilt .
Very well . I head a group of scientists ...
who would like to examine him and try and find out what it was ...
that drove him out of his mind .
We know what it were .
- Let him be . - Let him die .
Do you know for a fact he was the murderer ?
He made the killing happen .
It were he that were chosen , and he passed it to a brother .
The time will come when them that have no true belief shall be accursed .
What do you want to do with him ?
The authorities say that I 'll have to have the written permission ...
of the next of kin before he can be released to us .
So I was hoping you would sign this release paper , Mrs. Hobart .
And what will this examination do ?
We hope that under hypnosis ...
That 's a special technique we have ...
that we 'll be able to find out what he did and saw at the time of the killing .
You say it was his brother who died .
I didn 't realize it was one of the family .
A brother of the faith .
A true believer , not like him .
I 'll sign it as you ask .
Why do you do this for him ?
What be it to us what they want ?
Let them all know what he saw .
Well , thank you very much , Mrs. Hobart .
I 'll let you know what happens .
He has been chosen .
I 've been chosen for what ?
What do you mean ?
Let no arm be raised to defend him .
Defend me from what ?
That 's it , sir . Number 44 .
Thank you .
Over here , John .
I 'm sorry I 'm late . I just got back to the hotel and found your message .
It 's only a minute or two . I wanted to wait and go in with you .
- What is this all about ? - I 'm not sure I know .
That 's why I asked you to come here . I didn 't want to have to explain .
I promised Mrs. Karswell I 'd bring you here .
- Mrs. Karswell ? - John , she wants to help you .
I thought we might take a chance . I mean , I thought ...
at least we might learn something .
After this afternoon , I must confess there are a few things I don 't know .
I 'm so glad you 've come , both of you .
Mr. Meek has just telephoned . He 's on his way .
- May I ask who Mr. Meek is ? - The gentleman I want you to meet .
And this is Mrs. Meek . Miss Harrison ...
I mean Harrington , and Dr. Holden .
- How do you do ? - Excuse me , please .
Don 't you worry . All your problems will be solved . You 'll see .
That 's very nice . May I ask how ?
- Through tonight 's seance . - Seance ?
Yes . Mr. Meek is the most remarkable medium .
I come to him with all my problems . Here he is now .
John , she 's trying to help you .
I said I 'd talk to her . But this nonsense ...
- These things are all phony . - Oh , please .
You 'll hurt Mr. Meek 's feelings .
- He really is a most wonderful man . - Well , good evening .
' Tis a good evening too . A little warm , perhaps .
Mr. Meek , this is Dr. Holden .
So you 're the gentleman who was in trouble . Maggie , dear ?
Well , life 's full of little problems , isn 't it ?
Let 's see . What 's yours ? No , perhaps you better not tell me .
The spirits sometimes resent previous knowledge .
Well , let 's see if we can clear the air .
Not being part of the circle , you two had better sit by the window .
Well , Maggie , no point in wasting these good people 's time .
I must be insane to get involved in a thing like this .
John , please .
Very well , Maggie .
Cherry ripe Cherry ripe
Ripe , I cry
Full and fair ones
We must all sing . The spirits like it .
He 's going off .
That 's really very quick . He 's so helpful , you 'll see .
Mrs. Karswell ...
Something 's here . Can 't you feel it ?
That 's Crimson Eagle . He 's Mr. Meek 's guide .
He 's a Red Indian Chief from an obscure part of your country .
Well , a kindly good evening to you , friends .
Good evening , Mr. McGregor . That 's Mr. McGregor .
He always comes through . He 's a friend of ours .
Bonny weather we 're having .
It 'll do a mickle of good to the flowers and the barley .
Lovely weather , Mr. McGregor .
But I sense we have strangers in our midst .
Two strangers .
But they 're very sympathetic .
Will ya ha ' them into the circle ?
That 's really a great honor .
Mr. McGregor 's so particular who sits in the circle . Here .
Over here , both of you .
Mommy ! Oh , Mommy !
Somebody 's poor departed child . I wonder whose .
I can 't find ...
I can 't find Frederica .
She 's lost her doll .
- It 's my uncle . - Don 't be foolish .
- Are you there , Joanna ? - Yes .
- These things are all faked . - But it is my uncle ! I know his voice !
Please ! You 'll hurt Mr. Meek .
Got to ...
Got to tell Holden ...
he can 't fight it .
It 's too strong .
He means you must give up the investigation .
- This is crazy . - Karswell has the key .
He 's translated the old book .
The answer is there .
- No ! - Look !
It 's in the trees ! It 's coming !
The demon ! It 's coming ! No !
That does it .
Don 't turn the light on ! He 's in a trance !
- A trance my eye . - Maggie , I feel sick .
- You 're not the only one . - He 's still alive , no thanks to you .
Don 't you know that to wake a medium out of a trance is to risk his life ?
But it was real ! You must do as he says .
Don 't you understand ? Oh , dear .
Mr. Holden ! Don 't go , Mr. Holden !
Oh , Mr. Holden , you must listen ! Mr. Meek knew nothing !
Let them go . All right , Mother . Come along with me .
But I tell you , it did sound like my uncle 's voice .
It was Mr. Meek doing voice impersonations .
And your supposed friend , Mrs. Karswell , states the whole thing .
She 's looking out for her son 's interests , not mine .
Tomorrow 's the 28th .
That would be a real miracle if Karswell could change time .
What if we did find he really had a translation of that book .
Would that convince you that there is something in all this ?
It might help .
Then I 'm going to Karswell 's house to see if I can find it .
Go ahead .
Aren 't you even going to try to stop me ?
It would be easier to stop Karswell 's demon ...
than a woman who has her mind made up .
No lights are showing .
If anybody finds you there , the charge will be burglary .
Karswell is away . His mother told me .
If you find a reception committee waiting for you ...
will you believe then that Mrs. Karswell loves her son , not us ?
I hope that 's what does happen .
Don 't you see I want to be wrong ?
There 's nothing I 'd like better than to find out ...
that this is all being put on just to scare you off .
Where are you going ?
- To see if I can get into the house . - But it was my idea .
You didn 't think for a minute that I 'd let you go in there , did you ?
- I 'll go with you . - No , it 'll be much easier for me .
I can get next to the house by going through the woods without being seen .
And with you waiting , I 'll hurry back .
- Why did you drop the poker ? - It 's red-hot .
It isn 't , you know . My boy , you 're as pale as death .
There was something in here .
Nothing to worry you . Just a minor demon I set to protect the room .
Nothing like the real thing when you meet it .
It may have been minor , but it had claws and teeth .
Oh , claws and teeth .
Did you bite the man ? Oh , shame .
I don 't keep you as a watch cat . I left the book in full sight for him .
His name is Greymalkin .
A very fashionable name for English cats in the Middle Ages .
- They were used in witchcraft . - It was not that cat .
Oh , yes , it was . You must have awakened him .
You shouldn 't have , at the time of the full moon ...
when cats wander and witches dance .
Oh , yes . They do dance . I 've seen them .
- You really are crazy , aren 't you ? - On the contrary . You seem unhinged .
Is breaking into my house to read my scribbles an indication of sanity ?
- I was talked into that . - Ah , Miss Harrington , no doubt ...
that horribly bright young woman .
- I don 't think she 'd be flattered . - At least her head isn 't in the sand .
She believes that she can see . She can .
She believes that she 's alive . She is .
She believes that you 'll die tomorrow night . You will .
Julian , I thought I heard ...
It 's all right , Mother . Just a social visit . Dr. Holden was just leaving .
- Is your car outside ? - Housebreakers don 't leave cars .
You have a point there . Give my regards to that intelligent young woman .
If you 're thinking of going through the woods , you might find it unpleasant .
I suggest you use the drive . I 'll put on the light for you .
I have one superstition ... I like to go back the way I came .
He 's a very obstinate young man .
I told him not to go through the woods . He just wouldn 't listen .
It was dark in the trees ...
and I saw this smoke .
I know this sounds crazy , but ...
I could 've sworn the smoke came after me .
And don 't forget Karswell tore out those pages .
I mean , the book must have had the answer .
Why would he have torn them out otherwise ?
Quite . One usually has a reason for tearing things out .
And this feeling of being followed .
And Karswell says Dr. Holden will die tomorrow night .
Of this enchantment thing ?
Forget the hex . Let 's say something came after me . Take it from there .
We 've been through all of this before .
Frankly , I think a bit of sleep is indicated .
It 's extraordinary how different a thing can look in the morning .
- But there 's so little time ! - If what you say is true .
- But it is ! All of it ! - Doctor ...
I don 't think Scotland Yard can be anything but an interested spectator .
- I see your point . - You mean , Uncle , you have a victim ?
You already have one ... my uncle .
Have we got anything in criminal records to cover phantoms and demons ?
- Not that I know of . - I didn 't think so .
You 're right . It will seem different in the morning .
But it is morning . It 's 3 : 00 in the morning , to be exact .
If you insist on setting the wheels grinding , will you please wait here ?
Spare me a minute , sir . There 's a Dr. John Holden outside , sir .
- The psychology chap ? - That 's it , sir .
It 's ... It 's a bit awkward . He 's ...
It seems he 's bewitched .
You know , broomsticks and all that . Thinks he 's being followed by something .
Apparently , he 's going to die tomorrow night .
- Does he say so ? - Well , not exactly , sir .
There 's a young lady with him , a Miss Harrington .
Apparently , her uncle went through the same thing .
Thought he was being followed by something or other .
Thought he was going to die on a certain night at 1 0 : 00 .
Did he ?
That 's the thing that 's got me puzzled , sir . He did .
You look angry .
Maybe that 's because I am .
- With me , for bringing you here ? - No . At myself ...
for not realizing what their attitude was bound to be .
Look , Joanna , let me tell you something about myself .
When I was a kid , I used to walk down the street with the other kids .
When we 'd come to a ladder , they 'd all walk around it .
I 'd walk under it , just to see if anything would happen .
Nothing ever did . When they 'd see a black cat ...
they 'd run the other way to keep it from crossing their path .
But I didn 't , and all this ever did for me ...
was make me wonder why ...
why people could get so panicky over absolutely nothing at all .
I 've made a career studying it ...
maybe just to prove one thing ...
that I 'm not a superstitious sucker like about 90 percent of humanity .
But what did you run from in the woods ?
It was a trick gadget that Karswell had rigged up to frighten me away ...
and I fell for the bait like an idiot .
But he told you himself not to go back through the trees .
That 's good psychology .
The same as he used when he had your sweet old Mrs. Karswell ...
plant the story about his being away .
Don 't bother about him .
He thinks I 'm crazy anyway . I 'm beginning to think so myself .
Allowing myself to be stampeded like this into a state of hysteria ...
I suppose you mean by me .
I didn 't say you were doing it deliberately .
But that 's what you meant . Good night , Dr. Holden .
When your partner comes out , tell him it was just a bad Halloween joke .
I want to clear up everything today , even if it means ...
having the closing session tonight .
- Is that all right with you ? - Fine .
Hobart 's been send down today by ambulance under guard .
I want to get back to the States as soon as possible .
I 'll get it . You finish your breakfast .
Yes ? Who 's calling ?
It 's Mrs. Karswell .
Tell her I cut my throat . Anything . Get rid of her .
She 's been calling all night .
Dr. Holden has just left for the day . I 'm sorry .
Hmm ? She 's hung up .
Karswell 's working his mother overtime .
Let 's go , shall we ?
Hello ? Oh , yes , Mrs. Karswell .
I 've tried to get Mr. Holden all day , but he won 't take a call .
I thought perhaps you could get through to him .
Believe me , I was as much surprised ...
by Julian 's return last night as you were .
I think I found another way to help Mr. Holden .
I 'm not certain that he needs help .
And even if he does , I 'm quite sure that he doesn 't want it from me .
But you can 't mean that , surely .
You must listen to me . Someone else knows the secret of the parchment .
Tell him Rand Hobart knows .
All this evil must end , Miss Harrington .
It must end .
I must ring off now .
- Yes , Mother ? - Please , Julian , try to understand .
I 'm afraid it 's you who don 't understand .
All of us here know that through the use of hypnotism ...
we can unlock certain sections of the human mind ...
that are not accessible to memory .
A great deal of publicity has been given lately ...
to hypnotized persons who supposedly recall ...
an existence prior to birth .
In all cases , we must ask ourselves ...
" Do hypnotized people always tell the truth ? "
The subject of hypnotism brings us to a presentation ...
of the late Professor Harrington 's study and investigation ...
of people who follow witch cults ...
and practice devil worship .
We 're going to perform an experiment on the platform ...
with a Mr. Rand Hobart ...
who , through an experience related to devil worship ...
has lost all contact with reality .
Professor O 'Brien , the platform is yours .
We have here an extraordinary subject .
For a period of time , this man has been as you see him here .
He fails to respond to any normal stimulation .
His experience , whatever it was ...
which we hope here to discover , has left him ...
in a state of absolute catatonic immobility .
When I first investigated this case , the problem of how to hypnotize ...
an unresponsive person was the major one .
Now , the proceedings may be somewhat dramatic , but they are necessary .
The only way of bringing his mind out of the womb of darkness ...
into which it has retreated to protect itself ...
is by therapeutic shock ... electrical or chemical .
For our purpose , we are today using pentathol ...
and later methyl amphetamine .
Hobart , look at this .
Look at this . You see only this .
You see nothing else . Only the light .
Only this .
You see only the light .
Look at this .
You see only this .
You see nothing else .
Your eyelids are getting heavy .
Tired .
More and more tired .
You 're going to sleep .
Sleep .
Calm , restful sleep .
Rest . Sleep .
Now .
You hear nothing but my voice .
Do you understand , Hobart ?
The patient is now in a deep trance and will obey the commands of Dr. Holden .
Methyl amphetamine .
- Do you wish to proceed ? - No , I 'll turn him over to you .
Hobart , you 'll next hear the voice of Prof. O 'Brien .
From that point on , it will be his voice and his alone ...
that you will hear and obey .
Do you understand that ?
Yes ?
- Do you hear me ? - Yes .
Mine is the only voice you 'll hear . Is that clear ?
Yes . Only you .
Hobart , what is the order of the true believer ?
Those of us who believe that ...
evil is good ...
and good evil .
Yes , go on .
Who blaspheme ...
and desecrate ...
in the joy of sin where mankind that is lost ...
will find itself again .
And who revealed this to you , Hobart ?
Who ?
The one who has brought us the wisdom ...
of the true belief .
- Julian Karswell ? - Yes .
Now , I want you to come forward in time .
It is the night of the demon .
You must .
No ! It 's there .
I see it in the trees ...
the smoke and the fire .
My time allowed is almost over .
Hobart , what do you mean , " your time allowed " ?
He 's not in rapport with you . Want me to turn him over ?
- Yes , please . - Hobart ...
from now on , the only voice you 'll hear is that of Dr. Holden .
Do you understand ?
What do you mean by " your time allowed " ?
To prepare for my death .
Why must you die ?
I 've been chosen .
How will you die ?
The parchment was passed to me .
I took it without knowing .
Hobart , open your eyes .
Is this the parchment ?
I passed it back to the brother who gave it to me .
It was the only way . I had to return it to him .
I didn 't want to , but it was the only way I could save myself .
To save yourself , you had to give it back to the one who gave it to you ?
Yes . Yes . I had to .
And the demon took him .
Not me ! Not me !
You 're trying to pass it to me again .
But I won 't take it .
I won 't !
Let it escape ! Let it escape !
It was born in fire !
Let it die in fire !
Oh , this is terrible .
Really terrible .
Could you get me a car to take me to Lufford Hall ?
You can use mine . But why should you want to go there ?
I have something to return to Mr. Karswell . Give me the key .
Certainly .
Dr. Holden . Wait .
- I do not believe he 's there . - How do you know ?
Mrs. Karswell told me earlier on the telephone .
Knowing your attitude , I told her you would not be interested . Are you ?
- Yes , I am . - She kept saying all evil must end ...
but how could it ?
- Go on . - I hardly understood her ...
but it seems that her son is taking the 8 : 45 train to Southampton tonight .
- Would you know why ? - The 8 : 45 .
Has the Southampton train come through yet ?
- She 's in the station now . - Give me one ticket , please .
Good evening , Dr. Holden .
My boy . I 've been expecting you .
Joanna . First-stage hypnosis .
Oh , just a convenient way of stopping idle chatter on the train .
She 's not harmed . I 'll bring her out of it .
Now , wake .
There 's a friend here . Talk to him .
- John . - This is abduction , you know .
Oh , dear me , no , no , no .
She came quite willingly .
You came willingly , didn 't you ?
You remember . We discussed it ...
oh , at great length .
John , he 's frightened ... terrified of you .
I thought it was supposed to be the other way around .
- He 's trying to run away from you . - You see why I let her sleep ?
This idle chatter .
Karswell , I know now ...
that you were right and I was wrong .
Really ?
But there is a way out for me . You always said so .
- Here . - What 's this ?
Read it .
You want me to admit your power . You can send this to any newspaper ...
and photostatic copies to all your followers .
- Isn 't that what you want ? - Yes , but it 's too late now .
It 's six minutes to 10 : 00 .
Well , I guess it was my fault for not listening to Joanna .
I 'm sorry now that I didn 't listen .
And I want to thank you for convincing me ...
of the existence of a world I never thought possible .
Oh , if only you 'd understood sooner .
I suppose ...
I still have time for a last cigarette .
No , thank you . I 've stopped smoking .
It must have been quite recently .
- Have you got a match ? - Yes , of course .
Thank you .
That 's all right . You keep them . I shan 't need them anymore .
You 're very generous .
Well , I 'll leave you two alone .
I know there 's a certain feeling between you , and you might want to be alone .
Sit down . Your generosity is becoming overwhelming as it gets closer to 10 : 00 .
You 're staying with me , Karswell .
You 've sold your bill of goods too well , because I believe you now .
I believe that in five minutes ...
something monstrous and horrible is going to happen .
And when it does , you 're going to be here ...
so that whatever happens to me will happen to you .
You 're insane . You can 't do this .
No ? You 're staying here , Karswell .
- You 're staying right here . - No !
Let him go , Holden !
- This man 's insane . I must go . - It 's all right , Doctor .
We 're the police , as Holden knows .
We 've had you under observation at his request .
- Fortunately for you , as you can see . - Yes , I see . Thank you .
It 's obvious that Holden has got a bit of a persecution complex about you .
Something about your putting a hex on him .
That 's ridiculous . If you 'll excuse me , I 'm getting out of this station .
Johnny , he 's lying . He bought a ticket to Southampton . I saw it myself .
This is idiotic . I can leave this train when I want .
- Excuse me . - Here 's your book .
It 's not mine . I found it here when I got on the train .
- Your bag , sir ? - My bag ... Oh , yes .
- Yes , of course . - These are his too .
You want your hat and coat , don 't you , sir ?
Oh , yes . Very forgetful of me . Thank you very much .
You passed them .
You slipped them in my pocket .
- It 's two minutes of 10 : 00 . - Come on .
- What was that ? - Come on .
- There 's a man on the track ! - What happened ?
I don 't know , but I think the train 's hit him .
Maybe it 's better not to know .
The train must have hit him and dragged him .
I thought he was on the other side , sir .
Don 't be ridiculous , Simmons . Look at him .
The train must have hit him .
You 're right . Maybe it 's better not to know .